Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Science Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Biology
    - Tran, Thinh. Determining the identities and functions of missing temporal transcription factors in the Drosophila optic lobes, 2017; 2017-0037; The sequential expression of transcription factors (TFs) in neural progenitors activates or represses different genes, and thus generates different types of neurons from a homogenous pool of stem cells. In the fruit fly, neuroblasts that give rise to the optic lobes sequentially express five TFs to specify different neural fates. However, two TFs in the cascade fail to regulate each other's expression, in contrast to the other three TFs, which suggests that there exists at least one missing TF that acts between them. This study aims to identify the missing TF(s) through a genetic screen. After testing the potential of ~190 TFs for being part of the temporal cascade, I identified three primary candidates, Nuclear factor Y (NF-Y), homeobrain and max. The knowledge of the missing TF will allow us to further examine how temporal patterning progresses and contributes to the generation of neuronal diversity in the optic lobe. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0037)
      The sequential expression of transcription factors (TFs) in neural progenitors activates or represses different genes, and thus generates different types of neurons from a homogenous pool of stem cells. In the fruit fly, neuroblasts that give rise to the optic lobes sequentially express five TFs to specify different neural fates. However, two TFs in the cascade fail to regulate each other's expression, in contrast to the other three TFs, which suggests that there exists at least one missing TF that acts between them. This study aims to identify the missing TF(s) through a genetic screen. After testing the potential of ~190 TFs for being part of the temporal cascade, I identified three primary candidates, Nuclear factor Y (NF-Y), homeobrain and max. The knowledge of the missing TF will allow us to further examine how temporal patterning progresses and contributes to the generation of neuronal diversity in the optic lobe.
    - Torres, Gabriel Figueroa. Impact of infection and treatment on epigenetic profiles of malarial children in Burkina Faso, 2017; 2017-0028; Malaria is a major public health problem with 3.3 billion individuals at risk in tropical and subtropical regions of the world and an estimated 438,000 deaths in 2015. Major advances have been made in understanding the epidemiology and pathobiology of the disease. However, little is know about the genetic and epigenetic mechanisms modulating variation in host immune response against the parasite. In this project, we investigate variation in genome-wide epigenetic profiles of circulating immune cells of children from Burkina Faso before and during infection, and after treatment using more than 850,000 epigenetic markers from the Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip. Our results revealed major and statistically significant changes in the epigenetic profiles of children in response both to infection and treatment and the genomic regions underlying these changes - including five genes within the human Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC). These results highlight the role epigenetic factors play in modulating response to malaria infection. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0028)
      Malaria is a major public health problem with 3.3 billion individuals at risk in tropical and subtropical regions of the world and an estimated 438,000 deaths in 2015. Major advances have been made in understanding the epidemiology and pathobiology of the disease. However, little is know about the genetic and epigenetic mechanisms modulating variation in host immune response against the parasite. In this project, we investigate variation in genome-wide epigenetic profiles of circulating immune cells of children from Burkina Faso before and during infection, and after treatment using more than 850,000 epigenetic markers from the Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip. Our results revealed major and statistically significant changes in the epigenetic profiles of children in response both to infection and treatment and the genomic regions underlying these changes - including five genes within the human Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC). These results highlight the role epigenetic factors play in modulating response to malaria infection.
    - Al Mheiri, Ghareesa. Probing the Structure of a Catalytically Active Unique Minimal Hammerhead Ribozyme and Determining its Biological Relevance, 2018; 2018-0087 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0087)
      Hammerhead Ribozymes (HHRs) are single-folded RNA motifs that undergo the reversible autocatalytic self-cleavage. The RNA motif of interest, N15, was found to carry out catalysis despite its stem-loop II structure being shorter. Two structural conformations were found to stabilize the core of the minimal N15min7, LCI (loop II-core interaction) and LSI (loop II-loop I interactions), which then facilitate catalytic activity of the RNA molecule. To further examine the HHR, N15min7 was assayed at 1 mM of MgCl2 to determine if these interactions are maintained at lower concentrations of divalent metal ions. When assaying the wild-type (WT) N15min7, LSI and LCI structures with deoxy-base substitution at lower concentrations of MgCl2, no significant difference in catalytic activity was observed among these three structures, indicating that an alternative interaction is taking place. Our results indicate that despite an overly simplistic structure, the N15min7 requires multiple interactions to catalyze self-cleavage at varying concentrations of divalent metal ions. Furthermore, the biological relevance of the N15min7 motif was determined by extensive computational searches for N15min7-like structures in a collection of ~8,000 genomes. The search identified ~100 instances of N15min7 sequences that can potentially form catalytically active structures.
    - Baby, Dhanya. Generation of a Wolbachia Secretome Resource for High-Throughput Analysis of Lymphatic Filariasis, 2018; 2018-0071 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0071)
      Lymphatic filariasis is caused by the parasitic nematode, Brugia malayi. These roundworms persist in the human host for years, and the suspected mechanism is immunomodulation of the human immune system. Most of the filarial nematodes including B. malayi harbour an endosymbiotic bacterium, Wolbachia in their lateral chords. The goal of this project was to generate a comprehensive resource to enable functional proteomics studies of the interactions between Wolbachia and human. We produced an Open Reading Frame (ORF) resource for high-throughput experimentation by synthesizing a subset of ORFs of secreted Wolbachial proteins. We successfully cloned over 80% of our synthesized ORFs into two destination vectors optimized for high-throughput experimentation, namely Yeast 2-Hybrid screening and protein expression. Gene expression analysis indicated genes up-regulated during infectious stages were associated with protein folding and chaperone functions, suggesting a likelihood of increased protein production during infectious stages. We also conducted in silico protein analysis to understand the function of protein products in our subset. Our genome-scale Yeast 2-Hybrid Screen with our cloned ORFs against the human ORFeome yielded 3 of the Wolbachial proteins, involved in DNA repair, potentially interacting with human gene products.
    - Bhagani, Humna. Exploring the role of the heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein CBF-A in neuronal development, 2018; 2018-0070 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0070)
      Posttranscriptional regulation of gene expression is an essential mechanism that controls development and differentiation in cells. Here, we focused on the role of the heterogeneous ribonucleoprotein CBF-A, known to regulate mRNA transport by binding the RNA trafficking sequence located on the 3' UTR of mRNA transcripts. We applied genome wide approaches to MEFs from a CBF-A KO mouse to examine whether CBF-A mediates RNA trafficking at an early stage during RNA biogenesis in developing neurons. RNA-seq analysis of CBF-A KO and heterozygous (HT) MEFs showed that there are many neuronal genes altered in the absence of CBF-A. We then chemically reprogrammed CBF-A KO and HT MEFs into neuron-like cells. Immunostaining confirmed differential expression of neuronal markers. To begin characterizing the induced neurons, we tested 150 neuronal and fibroblast- specific primers on WT MEFs and reprogrammed neurons to create a primer profile for future analyses. Results from this study confirm a primary role of CBF-A in RNA biogenesis and begins to highlight its importance in achievement of cell fate during neuronal development.
    - Choi, JooHee. Characterizing the Transposable Element Landscape of Date Palm (Phoenix dactylifera), 2018; 2018-0052 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0052)
      The date palm (Phoenix dactylifera) is a culturally and economically important crop across the Middle East, South Asia, and Northern Africa- yet our understanding of its genome remains relatively limited. This study aims to detect and characterize the transposable element (TE) landscape in this significant species through a novel combination of both library-based (Repeatmodeler) and k-mer based (REPdenovo) computational methods. The resulting consensus reads were masked via Repeatmasker and mapped to a gene map (NCBI: GCF_000413155.1_DPV01). Of the 500Mb genome assmbly, 38% was annotated as repetitive elements, of which LTR Copia and Gypsy were predominant. Comparison of element length and divergence indicate that LTR Copia elements are likely young and recently active. When mapped against regions upstream and downstream to genes, there was a relative abundance of Gypsy upstream compared to Copia, that may suggest an innate insertion bias at play. Of the elements uniquely assembled by REPdenovo, a majority were identified as plastid-derived sequences. Estimates suggest approximately 0.2% of the date palm genome consists of such elements, highlighting a category of plant DNA often overlooked. Through this study, we provide a TE-level understanding of the date palm genome structure that may act as a "roadmap" in future palm studies.
    - Degutis, Karolis. Investigation of Top-down and Bottom-up Signals in Visual Working Memory in V1, 2018; 2018-0076 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0076)
      Working memory (WM) allows for the maintenance of information over short periods of time when the initial source of the information is no longer present. In this study, we investigated whether the visual WM signal in the primary visual cortex (V1) is top-down or bottom-up using 3T functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). A top-down signal would indicate storage of visual WM outside of V1, while a bottom-up signal would indicate V1 maintenance. The direction of the signal was operationalized with an Attention and Perception task; each one activating distinct neural populations within V1. These patterns of activity were then compared using multivoxel pattern analysis (MVPA) to the pattern elicited from a visual WM task. The study replicated previous results by finding orientation-selective information present in V1 without a high-amplitude sustained BOLD response. We also found significant similarity between the patterns of the visual WM and Attention tasks. These results suggest a top-down signal in V1 during the maintenance of visual WM, consistent with the idea that visual WM is not maintained within V1.
    - Fadil, Chaimaa. Single-Cell Transcriptome Profiling of the Drosophila Optic Lobe Suggests a Regulation of Terminal Characters by Cell Type-Specific Transcription Factor Cohorts, 2018; 2018-0094 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0094)
      Understanding how a system comes to be and what its different components are is critical to deciphering its mode of action. In multicellular organisms, it is now established that transcription factors expressed during development play a key role in specifying cell fate. However, to better encompass cellular diversity, we are yet to understand how molecular specification translates into character acquisition. This study takes a holistic and unbiased approach to molecularly characterize cellular diversity in the adult Drosophila optic lobe based on Drop-seq single-cell RNA-seq of 57,000 cells. With unsupervised analysis and differential expression testing, I identified 52 clusters of transcriptionally distinct single-cell populations. I annotated several clusters by correspondence to known cell types on the basis of canonical markers or by characterizing cells' localization and projection patterns using Gal4 lines. Regulatory interactions between the transcription factors apterous and traffic-jam and the respective markers of cholinergic and glutamatergic neurons, ChAT and VGlut, were confirmed by gene knock-down through RNAi. Interestingly, these results, in addition to a weighted gene co-expression network analysis (WGCNA), showed that cell types with similar phenotypes do not necessarily share the same transcription factor signature, thus suggesting that phenotypic convergence is a likely cellular evolutionary model in Drosophila.
    - Govind, Jigar. Long-Term Balancing Selection at MHC class I loci in the Ethiopian frog Leptopelis gramineus, 2018; 2018-0077 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0077)
      In the defense against diseases, organisms must maintain a repertoire of molecules that can respond to the variety of pathogens in their habitat. The variety of pathogenic threats present in one's surroundings depends on several environmental variables, including climate. Here I isolated and analyzed class I MHC sequences from the Ethiopian frog Leptopelis gramineus, sampled across a heterogeneous habitat range, to investigate the relationship between demography, population structure and climate in the context of immunogenetic variation. I hypothesized that the signature of balancing selection is stronger in warmer climates. I used neutral markers to reconstruct the demographic history of each clade belonging to L. gramineus, measured genetic diversity, differentiation, and gene flow, and simulated these measures against neutral scenarios. While intra-specific subpopulation Tajima's D and Fu and Li's analyses revealed strong evidence for balancing selection, inter-specific analysis revealed a lack of clear genetic structure at MHC class I loci with respect to differences in clade, elevation difference, and geographical distance. Instead, the data demonstrate clear effects of long-term balancing selection that may predate the spatial dispersal of L. gramineus across Ethiopia.
    - Jankauskas, Robertas. During differentiation nuclear beta-actin regulates neuronal gene programs, 2018; 2018-0064 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0064)
      During the process of cellular differentiation global changes in chromatin lead to genome organization and the suppression and activation of gene programs. Emerging evidence indicates that nuclear β-actin is a major regulator of genome organization. β-actin performs this important function by regulating genomic deposition of the BAF chromatin remodeling complex. This leads to tethering of heterochromatin to the NL while controlling the level of euchromatin. To further study the role of nuclear actin in these processes and its potential impact on development and differentiation, here we implemented a direct reprogramming protocol on embryonic fibroblasts from a β-actin knockout mouse to directly reprogram them into induced neurons. We report differences in neuronal morphology between WT, HET, and KO cell lines arising from differential gene expression levels. Many of the compromised genes were found to be downregulated in a β-acting dosage dependent manner. GO term analysis found that these changes compromised programs related to neuronal development. Reintroducing an NLS containing β-actin in the KO cells positively affected neuron specific marker expression. Because the model organism is embryonic lethal at developmental stage 10.5 we conclude that nuclear β-actin helps regulate neuronal gene expression during development.
    - Kirwan, Liam Ingmar. Identification of Natural Products from Sponge/Tunicate-Associated Bacterial Species in the Abu Dhabi Region, 2018; 2018-0072 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0072)
      Marine invertebrate-associated bacteria are a promising source of natural products, especially in harsh conditions (such as Abu Dhabi) where metabolitefacilitated adaptation is necessary. This paper outlines a method of advanced bacterial isolation and high-content screening of crude bacterial cell extracts and SPE fractions, with the aim of identifying biologically active natural products through a process of cytological profiling and image analysis. Mammalian cell and C. elegans screens revealed the presence of a significantly toxic compound produced by a Vibrio sp. proteobacterium along with several other compounds that exhibit some form of phenotypic effect. Liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry was performed to provide insight into the potential chemical formulae of biologically active compounds. Phenotypic profiles and mass spectra were created for all active fractions, providing a solid foundation for future characterization of chemical structure and mode-of-action.
    - Manzoor, Ridda. Regulation of Transposon Expression by DNA methylation in Zebrafish uhrf1 mutants, 2018; 2018-0092 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0092)
      DNA methylation is a major epigenetic modification and its loss is associated with autoimmune disease, re-expression of oncogenes and the activation of transposable elements (TEs). This project aimed to investigate the relationship between TE expression and DNA methylation, as well as characteristics of TEs that could be contributing to expression. Previous RNA-seq analysis identified the top 10 upregulated TEs in uhrf1 mutants as compared to wild type (WT) larvae. Here, I analyzed the genomic features of these TEs and their pattern of expression by in situ hybridization (ISH). Bioinformatics analysis showed a significant correlation (r=0.6328 for WT and r=0.5871 for uhrf1 mutants) between read counts and number of full length reads. ISH showed significant expression of TEs in both the WT and uhrf1 mutant larvae, particularly in the brain, eyes and jaws. In the mutants, we observed a difference in signal in some TEs, but not major differences in the pattern of expression between WT and uhrf1 mutants. Phylogenetic analysis of the reverse transcriptase domains of the LTR Gypsy elements showed that Gypsy117-I_DR expressed the greatest fold change.
    - Mo, Ziyi. Phylogenetics of date palm (Phoenix dactylifera) and closely related wild species elucidates the nature of introgressive hybridization between North African date palm and Phoenix theophrasti, 2018; 2018-0086 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0086)
      The domestication history of date palm (Phoenix dactylifera), an important staple crop in the Middle East and North Africa, is not well understood. The popular model of domestication argues that date palm originated from the Middle East and later spread westward to North Africa via trade routes. However, higher observed nucleotide diversity within the North African date palm population suggests that the North African population is not the product of recent colonization, thereby contradicting the model. This study of 71 date palm cultivars from across Middle East and North Africa and 6 of its closely related wild species reconciles the higher observed nucleotide diversity in North African population and the popular domestication model by demonstrating that the North African date palm population is a result of introgressive hybridization between date palm and P. theophrasti. Linkage disequilibrium analysis and phylogeny of phased haplotypes in highly introgressed genomic region provide evidence for intro- gression, whereas chloroplast and mitochondrial phylogeny reveals that hybridization occurred through pollination of date palm offshoots by P. theophrasti.
    - Nehme, Mona. Adaptation of mitochondrial Oxidative Phosphorylation Genes to High Altitude in Leptopelis gramineus, 2018; 2018-0049 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0049)
      Harsh environmental conditions are common characteristics of high altitudes, such as those in the Ethiopian highlands. This can be detrimental to the survival of maladapted organisms, yet these areas continue to be biodiversity hotspots. This alludes to adaptive selection that equips high altitude organisms, such as Ethiopian endemic frog Leptopelis gramineus, with the capacity to survive in hazardous conditions. The mitochondrial genome has been previously shown to be crucial in adaptation due to it comprising of rapidly evolving non-recombining sequences. In this paper, I studied the role played by mtOXPHOS genes in adaptation to high altitude in L. gramineus using aBSREL, FEL, and MEME analytical methods. Diversifying selection was found in codons 42 in ATP8 and 311 and 317 in ND1. However, this selection could not be attributed to adaptation to high altitude considering the individuals who expressed the necessary mutations were collected from varying altitudes. The result could also potentially be related to incomplete lineage sorting resulting from high mutation rates in the addressed codon positions. Therefore, further analysis is needed in order to determine the role of ATP8 and ND1 on L. gramineus high altitude adaptation.
    - Šabanović, Merima. What it takes to be at the top: The complex interrelationship between chronic social stress and social dominance, 2018; 2018-0103 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0103)
      Most animal societies are organized in dominance hierarchies that affect an individual's reproductive success and access to resources. Exposure to stress is one of many complex factors contributing to hierarchy formation, but a hierarchical status itself can be stress-inducing. I aimed to elucidate the complex relationship between stress and dominance by delineating how social rank predicts vulnerability to social stress and whether chronic stress modulates hierarchy establishment. Using the C57 mouse model, hierarchical rank is studied using an automated social confrontation tube test that is consistent with at least three other dominance measures. Chronic social stress is mimicked by the chronic social defeat (CSD) paradigm that induces a depressive-like phenotype in stress-susceptible mice. I show that exposure to chronic stress predicts higher success in subsequent hierarchy formation. The mice that underwent CSD exhibited markedly higher winning ratios than their stress-naïve conspecifics. Results also suggest that the differences in social competitiveness are not related to the overall differences in stress-susceptibility, but hierarchical status may predispose the subordinate ranks to decreased baseline social preference. In contrast, dominant males are liable to higher anxious-like behavior following CSD-stress. Furthermore, I also demonstrate how individual housing conditions markedly increases a range of anxiety-like behaviors. I additionally report preliminary data on a neural circuit potentially underlying dominance- and stress-specific signal integration.
    - Saleh, Hadi Omar. CPP-Cargo Complex Translocation in Model Membrane Systems: Experiments and Simulations, 2018; 2018-0057 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0057)